<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Arpit Mittal</title>
        <link>https://0xarpit.in/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Arpit Mittal</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 17:37:09 +0530</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://0xarpit.in/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Vulnerability Management Process</title>
            <link>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2023/04/vulnerability-management-process/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 17:37:09 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2023/04/vulnerability-management-process/</guid>
            <description>What is Vulnerability Management? Vulnerability management is a process that involves identifying, assessing, and mitigating vulnerabilities in an organization&amp;rsquo;s systems and applications. The goal of vulnerability management is to proactively identify vulnerabilities before they can be exploited by attackers and to implement controls and mitigation strategies to reduce the risk of a successful attack.
The vulnerability management process typically involves the following steps:
Vulnerability Scanning Vulnerability Assessment Risk Prioritization Remediation Verification Continuous monitoring What is the need to establish Vulnerability Management process?</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
  
  
  
  <figure class="image is-3by2"
          
           data-align="center" >
    <img alt="cybersecurity career" src="/VM_hu01a84c255eee042d17f08865a630298a_102629_800x600_fit_box_3.png" />
  </figure>

<h3 id="what-is-vulnerability-management">What is Vulnerability Management?</h3>
<p>Vulnerability management is a process that involves identifying, assessing, and mitigating vulnerabilities in an organization&rsquo;s systems and applications. The goal of vulnerability management is to proactively identify vulnerabilities before they can be exploited by attackers and to implement controls and mitigation strategies to reduce the risk of a successful attack.</p>
<p>The vulnerability management process typically involves the following steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vulnerability Scanning</li>
<li>Vulnerability Assessment</li>
<li>Risk Prioritization</li>
<li>Remediation</li>
<li>Verification</li>
<li>Continuous monitoring</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-is-the-need-to-establish-vulnerability-management-process">What is the need to establish Vulnerability Management process?</h3>
<p>Organizations need a vulnerability management process to identify and mitigate security vulnerabilities in their systems and applications. Here are some reasons why vulnerability management is essential:</p>
<p><strong>1.  Proactive security:</strong> A vulnerability management process allows organizations to take a proactive approach to security. By identifying and mitigating vulnerabilities before they can be exploited by attackers, organizations can reduce their risk exposure and prevent potential security breaches.</p>
<p><strong>2.  Compliance requirements:</strong> Many industries and regulations require organizations to have a vulnerability management process in place. Compliance requirements may include regular vulnerability scans, risk assessments, and remediation activities.</p>
<p><strong>3.  Reputation and trust:</strong> Security breaches can damage an organization&rsquo;s reputation and erode customer trust. By implementing a vulnerability management process, organizations can demonstrate their commitment to security and protect their reputation.</p>
<p><strong>4.  Cost savings:</strong> A vulnerability management process can help organizations identify and mitigate vulnerabilities before they can lead to a security breach. By preventing security breaches, organizations can avoid the costs associated with remediation, legal fees, and reputational damage.</p>
<p><strong>5.  Competitive advantage:</strong> Organizations that have a strong security posture, including an effective vulnerability management process, can differentiate themselves from competitors and gain a competitive advantage.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-establish-the-vulnerability-management-process">How to establish the Vulnerability Management process?</h3>
<p>As a security engineer or lead, the following steps can be taken to establish a vulnerability management process in the organization:</p>
<p><strong>1.  Assess the current state of the organization&rsquo;s security:</strong> Before implementing any vulnerability management process, it&rsquo;s important to assess the organization&rsquo;s current security posture. This can be done by conducting a security assessment or audit to identify vulnerabilities and weaknesses in the organization&rsquo;s systems and processes.</p>
<p><strong>2.  Develop a vulnerability management plan:</strong> Based on the results of the security assessment, develop a vulnerability management plan that outlines the procedures and steps that will be taken to identify, assess, and mitigate vulnerabilities.</p>
<p><strong>3. Define roles and responsibilities:</strong> Establish clear roles and responsibilities for vulnerability management within the organization. Define who will be responsible for scanning, identifying, tracking, and mitigating vulnerabilities.</p>
<p><strong>4.  Conduct regular vulnerability scans:</strong> Conduct regular vulnerability scans on all systems and applications to identify any new vulnerabilities. Scans should be conducted on a regular basis, and after any significant changes to the network or systems.</p>
<p><strong>5.  Prioritize vulnerabilities:</strong> Prioritize vulnerabilities based on their severity and the impact they could have on the organization. This will help to focus on the most critical vulnerabilities first.</p>
<p><strong>6.  Develop a remediation plan:</strong> Develop a remediation plan to address identified vulnerabilities. The plan should include details on how vulnerabilities will be mitigated, who is responsible for the remediation, and the timeline for remediation.</p>
<p><strong>7.  Monitor remediation progress:</strong> Monitor the progress of remediation efforts to ensure that vulnerabilities are being addressed in a timely manner. Establish regular reporting and follow-up processes to ensure that vulnerabilities are being addressed.</p>
<p><strong>8.  Implement a continuous improvement process:</strong> Vulnerability management is an ongoing process that requires continuous improvement. Regularly review the vulnerability management plan, assess the effectiveness of the process, and make any necessary changes or improvements.</p>
<p><strong>9.  Train employees:</strong> Train employees on the importance of vulnerability management and how to report vulnerabilities. Encourage a culture of security within the organization, where employees are aware of their role in protecting the organization from cyber threats.</p>
<h3 id="pre-requisite-to-start-with-vulnerability-management-process">Pre-requisite to start with Vulnerability Management process</h3>
<p>Before starting with vulnerability management, there are several prerequisites that need to be in place. Here are some key prerequisites:</p>
<p><strong>1.  Asset Inventory:</strong> It&rsquo;s important to have an up-to-date inventory of all the hardware, software, and network devices in the organization. Without an accurate inventory, it will be difficult to identify vulnerabilities and prioritize remediation efforts.</p>
<p><strong>2.  Security Policy:</strong> The organization should have a security policy in place that outlines the standards, guidelines, and procedures for managing vulnerabilities. This policy should be communicated to all employees and stakeholders.</p>
<p><strong>3.  Vulnerability Scanning Tools:</strong> A vulnerability scanning tool is essential for identifying vulnerabilities in the organization&rsquo;s systems and applications. The tool should be capable of scanning all network devices, servers, and applications and should be configured to run on a regular basis.</p>
<p><strong>4.  Incident Response Plan:</strong> The organization should have an incident response plan in place to handle security incidents and vulnerabilities. The plan should include procedures for identifying, containing, mitigating, and reporting vulnerabilities.</p>
<p><strong>5.  Training:</strong> Employees should be trained on how to report vulnerabilities, the importance of vulnerability management, and how to follow the organization&rsquo;s security policies and procedures.</p>
<p><strong>6.  Resources:</strong> Adequate resources, including personnel and budget, should be allocated for vulnerability management. This includes hiring or training staff to manage the vulnerability management process and investing in tools and technologies to support the process.</p>
<h3 id="list-of-tools-for-vulnerability-management">List of tools for Vulnerability Management</h3>
<p>There are many tools available for vulnerability management, including both commercial and open-source options. Here are some of the most popular tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>Nessus</li>
<li>Qualys</li>
<li>OpenVAS</li>
<li>DefectDojo</li>
<li>Archery</li>
</ul>
<p>By following these steps, a security engineer or lead can establish a robust vulnerability management process in the organization that can help identify and mitigate vulnerabilities before they can be exploited by attackers.</p>
<p><em>Suggestions and improvements are always welcome. :)</em></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Career into Cybersecurity</title>
            <link>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2023/03/career-into-cybersecurity/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 17:37:09 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2023/03/career-into-cybersecurity/</guid>
            <description>How to Start a Career into Cyber Security? Cybersecurity has become an increasingly important field in today&amp;rsquo;s digital age. With the rise of cyber threats and data breaches, organisations and individuals are looking for ways to protect their sensitive information from malicious actors. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in starting a career in cybersecurity, there are a few steps you can take to get started.
Step 1: Learn the Basics and Domains of Cyber Security</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
  
  
  
  <figure class="image is-3by2"
          
           data-align="center" >
    <img alt="cybersecurity career" src="/cybersecurity-career_hu9b3a262b994fec9f66701fb9d8daf5d6_115644_800x600_fit_box_3.png" />
  </figure>

<h3 id="how-to-start-a-career-into-cyber-security">How to Start a Career into Cyber Security?</h3>
<p>Cybersecurity has become an increasingly important field in today&rsquo;s digital age. With the rise of cyber threats and data breaches, organisations and individuals are looking for ways to protect their sensitive information from malicious actors. If you&rsquo;re interested in starting a career in cybersecurity, there are a few steps you can take to get started.</p>
<p><strong>Step 1: Learn the Basics and Domains of Cyber Security</strong></p>
<p>Before you can dive into the world of cybersecurity, it&rsquo;s important to have a solid understanding of the basics. This includes understanding how computer systems work, the different types of threats that exist, and the techniques used to mitigate those threats.</p>
<p>There are many resources available online to help you learn the basics of cybersecurity. Websites like Youtube Channels [Cyber Mentor, Infosec4TC, TheHatedOne, NetworkChuck, Null Byte, John Hammond, Hak5, IppSec, LiveOverflow, GynvaelEN, etc], Coursera, Udemy, Cybrary and edX offer free and paid courses on various cybersecurity topics. Additionally, there are a number of books and online communities dedicated to cybersecurity that you can use to further your knowledge.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity is a complex and rapidly evolving field that covers a wide range of domains. Some of the main domains of cybersecurity include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Network Security:</strong> This domain focuses on securing the networks that connect devices and systems, including wired and wireless networks, routers, switches, and firewalls.</li>
<li><strong>Application Security:</strong> This domain is concerned with securing software applications and their associated data, including web applications, mobile apps, and desktop applications.</li>
<li><strong>Information Security:</strong> This domain involves protecting sensitive information from unauthorised access, modification, or destruction. This includes data encryption, access controls, and data backup and recovery.</li>
<li><strong>Operational Security:</strong> -   This domain covers the processes and procedures used to protect systems and data from internal and external threats, including physical security measures such as access controls, surveillance, and alarms.</li>
<li><strong>Disaster Recovery/Business Continuity Planning:</strong> This domain involves preparing for and responding to disasters or disruptions that could impact an organisations operations or IT infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Identity and Access Management:</strong> This domain is concerned with managing user identities and their access to systems and data, including authentication and authorisation processes.</li>
<li><strong>Cloud Security:</strong> This domain involves securing cloud-based systems and data, including Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS), Platform-as-a-Service (PaaS), and Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) offerings.</li>
<li><strong>IoT Security:</strong> This domain covers the security of Internet of Things (IoT) devices, including smart home devices, wearable technology, and industrial IoT (IIoT) systems.</li>
<li><strong>Social Engineering and Phishing:</strong> This domain covers the psychological manipulation of individuals to gain access to sensitive information or systems, including phishing attacks and social engineering scams.</li>
</ul>
<p>These domains are interdependent and require a holistic approach to cybersecurity to ensure the best possible protection against cyber threats.</p>
<p><strong>Step 2: Get Certified!</strong></p>
<p>Once you have a basic understanding of cybersecurity, it&rsquo;s time to get certified. There are a number of certifications available in the cybersecurity field, each with its own set of requirements and benefits. Some of the most popular certifications include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.comptia.org/certifications/security">CompTIA Security+</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.comptia.org/certifications/cybersecurity-analyst">CompTIA Cybersecurity Analyst (CySA+)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.eccouncil.org/train-certify/certified-ethical-hacker-ceh/">Certified Ethical Hacker (CEH)</a></li>
<li>eLearnSecurity Junior Penetration Tester (eJPT)</li>
<li><a href="https://elearnsecurity.com/product/ewpt-certification/">eLearnSecurity Web application Penetration Tester (eWPT)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://elearnsecurity.com/product/emapt-certification/">eLearnSecurity Mobile Application Penetration Tester (eMAPT)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Earning a certification can help demonstrate to potential employers that you have the skills and knowledge necessary to work in cybersecurity.</p>
<p><strong>Step 3: Gain Practical Experience</strong>
While certifications are important, they aren&rsquo;t enough on their own to secure a job in cybersecurity. To stand out from other candidates, it&rsquo;s important to gain practical experience in the field. This can include participating in cybersecurity competitions, contributing to open-source projects, or completing internships.</p>
<p>There are a number of resources to learn, such as the Hackthebox (HTB), Damn Vulnerable Web Application (DVWA), Damn Insecure and vulnerable App for Android (DIVA), Portswigger Web Security Academy, etc. Participating in these competitions can help you gain practical experience and demonstrate your skills to potential employers.</p>
<p>Additionally, contributing to open-source projects can help you build your portfolio (Github) and demonstrate your knowledge by writing blogs of cybersecurity tools and techniques.</p>
<p><strong>Step 4: Network</strong>
Networking is an important part of any career, and cybersecurity is no exception. Building connections with other professionals in the field can help you learn about job opportunities, gain mentorship, and stay up-to-date on the latest trends and techniques in cybersecurity.</p>
<p>One way to network in the cybersecurity field is to attend industry conferences, events and make connections on LinkedIn. These events offer opportunities to meet with other professionals and learn about the latest technologies and techniques in the field.</p>
<p>List of cyber security conferences:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nullcon.net/">NullCon</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.owaspseasides.com/">OWASP Seasides</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.securitybsides.com/w/page/12194156/FrontPage">BSides</a></li>
<li><a href="https://defcon.org/">DEFCON</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.blackhat.com/">Black Hat</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.rsaconference.com/en">RSA Conference</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Step 5: Apply for Jobs</strong>
Finally, it&rsquo;s time to apply for jobs in the cybersecurity field. Here are some job portals for cybersecurity professionals:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://jobs.null.community/">Null Jobs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.naukri.com/">Naukri</a></li>
<li><a href="https://in.linkedin.com/jobs">LinkedIN</a></li>
<li><a href="https://in.indeed.com/">Indeed</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.instahyre.com/">Instahyre</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cybersecjobs.com/">Cybersecjobs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cybersn.com/">CyberSN</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In the field of cybersecurity, the designations of freshers may vary depending on the organisation and the job roles they are hired for. However, some common entry-level job titles in cybersecurity include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cybersecurity Analyst</li>
<li>Information Security Analyst</li>
<li>Security Operations Center (SOC) Analyst</li>
<li>Cybersecurity Engineer</li>
<li>Network Security Engineer</li>
<li>Penetration Tester</li>
<li>Vulnerability Analyst</li>
<li>Security Consultant</li>
<li>Incident Response Analyst</li>
</ul>
<p>These roles may involve responsibilities such as monitoring network security, analysing threats and vulnerabilities, testing and evaluating security systems, managing access controls, and responding to security incidents. As freshers gain experience and skills, they can progress to more senior roles such as cybersecurity manager, cybersecurity architect, and chief information security officer (CISO).</p>
<p>When applying for jobs, be sure to tailor your resume and cover letter to the specific job and company you&rsquo;re applying to. Highlight your certifications, practical experience, and networking connections to stand out from other candidates.</p>
<p>In conclusion, a career in cybersecurity can be both challenging and rewarding. By learning the basics, getting certified, gaining practical experience, joining cybersecurity communities, and applying for cybersecurity jobs, you can start your journey towards a successful career in cybersecurity.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember, Cybersecurity is a constantly evolving field, so it&rsquo;s important to keep learning and adapting to stay ahead of the curve.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Note:</strong>  I&rsquo;m not promoting any certification or resources here, All the above mentions are for the help purpose only.</p>
<p>Suggestions and improvements are always welcome. :)</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>DevSecOps from Zero to Hero..!!</title>
            <link>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2022/12/devsecops-from-zero-to-hero../</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 17:37:09 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://0xarpit.in/posts/2022/12/devsecops-from-zero-to-hero../</guid>
            <description>Day by day we are learning different security approaches to minimize an improve the security gaps and for that we have to apply best possible security at all the levels. Now if we will talk about specifically for Application Security we can go with most preferred approaches which is SAST/DAST but do you think it is sufficient to secure your application as well as minimize the cost? The answer will be a big NO because while managing the whole application security domain we need to be ensured from the scratch and for this we have to start applying security best practices at the development level hence SSDLC (Secure Software Development Life Cycle) comes into the picture when we can train our developers to do the secure coding thus we can reduce the vulnerabilities count at the SAST and DAST level and then go for secure code review and dynamic security assessment process</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day by day we are learning different security approaches to minimize an improve the security gaps and for that we have to apply best possible security at all the levels. Now if we will talk about specifically for Application Security we can go with most preferred approaches which is SAST/DAST but do you think it is sufficient to secure your application as well as minimize the cost? The answer will be a big NO because while managing the whole application security domain we need to be ensured from the scratch and for this we have to start applying security best practices at the development level hence SSDLC (Secure Software Development Life Cycle) comes into the picture when we can train our developers to do the secure coding thus we can reduce the vulnerabilities count at the SAST and DAST level and then go for secure code review and dynamic security assessment process</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="what-if-we-can-automate-this-process">What if we can automate this process?</h3>
<p>Yes here we go with the DevSecOps process to use a secure code practice along with the best security solutions to innovate and ensure the data security and maintain the privacy. We cannot just rely on the scanners and reports to check the loopholes and check the weaknesses. We are already aware with the DevOps approach since a long time and now we need to add &lsquo;Security&rsquo; in between Development and Operation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>DevSecOps integrate security seamlessly into Agile environment along with the different development and security solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>DevSecOps is mostly in use to automate your CI/CD process along with the security. In this stage you&rsquo;ll define how you&rsquo;ll automate your process, how many stages you will be required for better CI/CD, what solutions you&rsquo;ll use in each stages to improve the security posture. These solutions can be open source or enterprise it&rsquo;s all depends upon your budget but in most of the stages you can use open source solutions to reduce the cost. I&rsquo;ve created below architecture as per my understanding with the each stages of DevSecOps:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>DevSecOps process include the development and operations posture of your organisation so that you can analyse and place the security. I&rsquo;ll recommend to create an architecture overview like what you&rsquo;re going to implement, define the stages of CI/CD, define what will be the processes involve in each stages, how you&rsquo;ll deploy the code, how you&rsquo;ll test your code, how you&rsquo;ll monitor the environment. For an example i&rsquo;ve created below architecture, this flow includes each stages along with the process/services:</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<h3 id="integration-of-open-source-solutions-into-pipeline">Integration of Open-source Solutions into Pipeline:</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s easy to integrate open-source solution into existing CI/CD pipeline to enhance the security but before that check the solution properly and customise it as per your requirement (If needed), We&rsquo;ve added few open-source solutions like Gitleaks, OWASP Dependency Checker, OWASP ZAP, etc. I&rsquo;ll share the reference below for further research. I&rsquo;ll also recommend to use any Vulnerability Management like Defectdojo to track the vulnerabilities.</p>
<h3 id="benefits-to-implement-devsecops">Benefits to Implement DevSecOps:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Rapid, cost-effective software delivery</li>
<li>Improved, proactive security</li>
<li>Accelerated security vulnerability patching</li>
<li>Automation compatible with modern development</li>
<li>A repeatable and adaptive process</li>
</ol>
<p>When we are saying DevSecOps it means continuation of integration and development along with the security. Here everyone can have a different mindset and approach to understand the DevSecOps process. When I&rsquo;ve started my research about develops I came across multiple resources and I&rsquo;ll recommend everyone to explore from yourself on the basis of your requirements.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
